A Guide to the Bishop William H. Marmion Papers 1932-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Bishop William H. Marmion Papers, (Ms86-013) 1932-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms86-013
The Papers include booklets, church bulletins, correspondence to and from Marmion, newspaper and magazine clippings, photographs, and reports generated by the Bishop in his service to the Episcopal Church.
Marmion, born 1907, was Episcopal Bishop of the Diocese of Southwestern Virginia from 1954 to 1979. The papers document the forty-seven year ecclesiastical career of William H. Marmion. Included are booklets, church bulletins, correspondence to and from Marmion, newspaper and magazine clippings, photographs, and reports generated by the Bishop in his service to the Episcopal Church. Topics of interest to the researcher include Marmion's interest in the civil rights movement, education, the Viet Nam War, Race relations in South Africa, and social relations among all Episcopalians.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research
Acquisition Information
Donated in 1986 by Bishop William H. Marmion of Roanoke, Virginia.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Houston, Texas on October 8, 1907, William H. Marmion was one of three children of Charles Gresham Marmion and Katherine Rankin Marmion. William Marmion grew up in Houston, and attended Christ Church in Houston. Graduating from Rice University in 1929, young Marmion entered the Virginia Theological Seminary, where he earned a bachelor's of divinity degree in 1932. Soon afterward, he was ordered deacon in the Episcopal Church, and on April 5, 1933 ascended to the priesthood. Starting his career in the ministry, the newly ordained priest returned to his native state, and served as Priest-in-Charge of two different churches: Taylor's St. James Church and Georgetown's Grace Church, from 1932-1935. The year 1935 was significant for another reason: William Marmion's marriage to Mabel "Blossom" Dougherty Nall on December 28, 1935.
After a brief tenure as Associate Minister of St. Mark's Church in San Antonio, Marmion received the appointment of Rector at Saint Mary's on the Highlands in Birmingham, Alabama, and occupied this position from 1938 until 1950. While in Birmingham, the Marimon's were blessed with two children, William Marmion, Jr., born on May 26, 1942, and Roger Mills Nall Marmion, born on January 19, 1944. In 1950, St. Andrew's Church in Wilmington, Delaware became his new parish, and the Rector remained until 1954. In this year William H. Marmion received a D.D. Divinity from the Virginia Theological Seminary, and later the same year was consecrated Bishop of the Diocese of Southwestern Virginia, a position he occupied until he retired in 1979.
Service to church and community punctuated the Bishop's life. Early in his career, Marmion became active in civic affairs serving in Youth Work in both Texas and Alabama. While in Birmingham, he also participated in the Department of Christian Social Relations of the Executive Council of the Diocese of Alabama, and for four years chaired the Alabama Committee on Interracial Cooperation. While at St. Andrew's, the Rector chaired the Department of Christian Education. These activities represented more than temporary assignments, for civil rights, education, and social relations among all Episcopalians remained life-longs interests.
After being consecrated Bishop in 1954, Marmion continued to focus on social issues. Opposed to unequal treatment of church members because of race and the War in Vietnam, the 1960's marked a troubled time in his career. In particular the five-year controversy (1957-1962) over the use of Hemlock Haven, a Diocesan retreat near Marion, Virginia, for biracial youth conferences proved to be a test of the Bishop's belief in equal treatment for all members of his diocese. Although at first the youth conferences were canceled due to the inability of the Diocese to come to an agreement on the terms of use, in 1963 Bishop's position prevailed, and the retreat finally hosted integrated youth conferences for young Episcopalian. The Bishop served on a number of committees that dealt with the topic of race and religion, including the Department of Christian Social Relations. Marmion also opposed American Involvement in the Vietnam Conflict, and his efforts to encourage an end to the conflict drew both support and sharp criticism from the members of his Diocese. Before retiring from his post as Bishop of Southwestern Virginia in 1979, Marmion participated in a number of church committees, including the Committee on World Relief and Interchurch Aid and the American Church Institute. He also chaired several committees, including the Church and Race Fund Committee and Long Range Planning Committee. Marmion also served on the Executive Council of the Episcopal Church from 1963-1969, and was active in establishing the Appalachian People's Service Organization, now Episcopal Appalachian Ministries, which was based in Blacksburg, Virginia before moving to Knoxville, Tennessee. After retiring as acting Bishop of the diocese, the Bishop and his wife continued to reside in Roanoke, Virginia.
Biographical Source:
Brown, Katharine. Hills of the Lord: Background of the Episcopal Church in Southwestern Virginia, 1738-1938. Roanoke, VA: The Diocese of Southwestern Virginia, 1979.
Scope and Content Information
The Bishop William Marmion Papers, comprised of forty-nine five-inch boxes, document the forty-seven year ecclesiastical career of William H. Marmion. The Papers include booklets, church bulletins, correspondence to and from Marmion, newspaper and magazine clippings, photographs, and reports generated by the Bishop in his service to the Episcopal Church.
The Marmion Papers are divided into four series. The first series, Personal Papers, is comprised of a variety of materials about the personal life of Marmion. Included in this series are photographs of the Bishop, biographical information, and newspaper clippings. Of note are a number of folders on social issues and events; examples include religion related performances such as Jesus Christ Superstar and Joseph and the Technicolor Dreamcoat. This series also includes brochures and maps on the sundry locales Marmion visited as a result of his travel to church related events.
The second series details Marmion's Early Career from 1932 until 1950. During this time Marmion served as a priest and rector in several churches in Alabama and Texas: as Priest in Charge at St. James Church in Taylor and Grace Church in Georgetown from 1932-1935, as Associate Minister of St. Mark's Church in San Antonio from 1935-1938, and as Rector of St. Mary's on the Highlands from 1938-1950. The majority of the material in this series are on issues related to the Marmion's work with the church, including his work with youth. A smaller third series covers the Bishop's tenure as Rector of St. Andrew's, Wilmington, Delaware, from 1950 through May 1954, and many of the documents in this series deal with the affairs of St. Andrew's Church.
The bulk of the Marmion Papers reside in series four, Bishop of Southwestern Virginia, 1954-1979. The series is divided into four sub-series: administrative, civil rights, international affairs, and the Vietnam War. The first sub-series, Administrative files, contains general administrative files relating to the Diocese of Southwestern Virginia and Marmion's duties in the Episcopal Church. Information includes a broad range of topics, including committee reports, diocesan reports, projects and programs undertaken by both the church and diocese, and correspondence related to the day to day operations of the diocese.
Contents of the second sub-series, Civil Rights, include brochures, correspondence, magazine articles, and newspaper articles which Marmion either collected or produced on the civil rights movement, mainly from the 1950's and 1960's. Included in this series are documents relating to the controversy over the biracial conferences at Hemlock Haven, a retreat near Marion, Virginia purchased by the diocese in 1957. While Marmion maintained the view that the youth conferences should be open to members of both races, many lay members of the diocese opposed mixed race conferences for young people, and only after five years of debate did the facility open to camps attended jointly by whites and African-Americans. The Bishop's yearly files on race relations from 1954-1965 also offer firsthand insight on the civil rights movement in the United States.
The third sub-series, International Affairs, includes correspondence and related documents detailing the Bishop's activities in overseas affairs. A large number of the folders detail companion diocese relationships with churches in Great Britain and Ecuador, and under the umbrella of this liaison Marmion made visits to both countries. Also included in this sub-series are documents that outline Marmion's opposition to apartheid in South Africa. Believing economic sanctions were key to forcing the South African government to end the racial discrimination of the apartheid system, in 1969 the Bishop chaired a committee to prevent the Episcopal Church from using banks which supported that country's government. Marmion's argument was persuasive, and the church agreed not to utilize banking firms who financed South Africa.
The fourth and smallest sub-series, Vietnam War, includes brochures, correspondence, magazine articles, and newspaper clippings on the war in Vietnam between 1964 and 1975. The Bishop advocated ending the conflict in Southeast Asia, and his participation in a public anti-war demonstration in Roanoke drew the ire of some of his parishioners. Called both communist and un-patriotic, Marmion nevertheless sought to influence the United States government to seek an end to military involvement in Vietnam.
Note to Researchers:
The major portion of the papers is original correspondence either to or from the Bishop. Although a conscious effort has been made to adhere to the original order, the choice was made to arrange the papers topically by subject to provide quicker, more succinct access to the papers. Researchers should note, however, that the original titles of the folders were maintained, and that many folders can contain a variety of information beyond the scope of the title. Related collections held by Virginia Tech include the Episcopal Diocese of Southwestern Virginia (Ms 1985-004) and the Appalachian Peoples Service Organization Records (Ms 1988-095).
Contents List
- Personal Papers
  30 linear inches. (6 document boxes). Consists of brochures, maps, papers, pamphlets, and photographs related to the Bishop's personal interest in social issues, his travel, personal photographs, and information about his family.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Austin, Texas (Box-folder 111)
  - Black Lung (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Bi-Centennial of American Independence (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Books (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Boston, Cape Cod, and Vicinity (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Boy Scouts (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Burrell Memorial Hospital (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Canada (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Career Evaluation (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Catacomb Cassette Club, The (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Cassettes (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions' Report to the President (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Chaplain, U.S. Senate (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Charismatic Movement (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Choir (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Chrisitian Friends: The Anti-Defamation League Bulletin (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Christmas Cards (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Church Issues (Map-case 2-5)
  - Civil War (U.S.) (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Clergy-Laity Schism (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Comfortable Pew, The (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Communication (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Communicating the Gospel (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Confession of 1967 (Presbyterian) (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Consultant to Bill Folwell, Central Florida (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Cybernetics, Automation, and the Church (Map-case 2-13)
  - Denominationalism (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Depression, The (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Deputy, The (Box-folder 2-16)
  - El Paso, Texas (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Energy Crisis, The (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Grounds for Encouragement (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Hurricane Camille (Box-folder 2-20)
  - General Thanksgiving, The (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Ivan Illich (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Jesus Christ Superstar (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Jesus Movement, The (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Holy Cross Magazine (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Law (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Law and Order (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Los Angeles, California (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Maine (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Marmion Photographs (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Mandantory Sentences (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Minnis Case--The Bishop (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Mobile, Alabama (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 3-14)
  - National Cathedral Association (Box-folder 4-1)
  - National Defense (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Necrology (Box-folder 4-3)
  - New Hampshire (Box-folder 4-4)
  - New York City (Box-folder 4-5)
  - New York State (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Occult Revival, The (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Operation Fuel (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Pari-Mutuel Gambling (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Patterson, Juan A. (Map-case 4-10)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Personal (Box-folder 4-12)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Box-folder 4-13)
  - Population Explosion (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Prison Reform (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Registrations (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Religion in the News (Box-folder 4-17)
  - Richmond (Box-folder 4-18)
  - Roanoke Historical Society (Box-folder 4-19)
  - Space Age, The (Box-folder 4-20)
  - Strip Mining (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Third World, The (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Tillich, Paul (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Trust Relationship, A (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Twentieth Century Theology and Theologians (Box-folder 5-5)
  - Urban Life (Box-folder 5-6)
  - United Campus Chapel (Box-folder 5-7)
  - Vermont (Box-folder 5-8)
  - Watergate (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Who's Who in America (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Wilmington, Delaware (Box-folder 6-2)
  - Witness, The (Box-folder 6-2)
  - W.S.G.N--Morning Devotion (Box-folder 6-4)
  - 1970's, The (Box-folder 6-5)
- Early Career 1932-1950
  12 linear inches (3 document boxes) this series focuses on the Bishop's early career as a priest and a Rector in both Texas and at St. Mary's in the Highlands, in Birmingham, Alabama. Topics include youth work, race relations, and church calls.
  - Anti-Defamation League (Box-folder 7-1)
  - Bulletin Material (Box-folder 7-2)
  - Brotherhood of St. Andrew (Box-folder 7-3)
  - Bush, Hollis (Box-folder 7-4)
  - Call to Corpus Christi (Box-folder 7-5)
  - Calls to Washington (Box-folder 7-6)
  - Church Fire Insurance Corporation (Box-folder 7-7)
  - Church School (Box-folder 7-8)
  - Church Society for College Work (Box-folder 7-9)
  - Church World Service (Box-folder 7-10)
  - Churchways (Box-folder 7-11)
  - CIO Organizing Committee (Box-folder 7-12)
  - Cleric's Scrapbook (Box-folder 8-1)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings (Box-folder 8-2)
  - Committee for Alabama (Box-folder 8-3)
  - Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy (Box-folder 8-4)
  - Community Chest (Box-folder 8-5)
  - Curate (Box-folder 8-6)
  - Division of Religious Education (Box-folder 8-7)
  - Episcopal Pacifist Fellowship (Box-folder 8-8)
  - Episcopal League for Social Action (Box-folder 8-9,10)
  - Every Member Canvass (Box-folder 8-11)
  - Fair Employment Practices Committee (Box-folder 8-12)
  - International Fellowship for Reconciliation (Box-folder 8-13)
  - Fellowship of Southern Churchmen (Box-folder 8-14)
  - Forward in Service (Box-folder 8-15, 16, 17)
  - Forward in Service (Box-folder 9-1)
  - Forward Today (Box-folder 9-2)
  - Hold (Box-folder 9-3)
  - Interparochial Institute (Box-folder 9-4)
  - Juvenile Delinquency (Box-folder 9-5)
  - Kanuga Lake Conference Center (Box-folder 9-6)
  - Letters to Congressmen (Box-folder 9-7)
  - Out of Town Bulletins (Box-folder 9-8)
  - St. Mary's Girl Club (Box-folder 9-9)
  - St. Mary's--School Teachers and Officers (Box-folder 9-10)
  - Women in Foreign Mission Fields (Box-folder 9-11)
  - Young Churchmen's Convention (Box-folder 9-12)
- Rector of St. Andrews, Wilmington, Delaware 1950-1954
  10 inches (2 document boxes)Many of the documents in this series deal with the Affairs of St. Andrew's Church.
  - Bishop's Election--Diocese of Delaware (Box-folder 10-1)
  - Builders for Christ (Box-folder 10-2)
  - Building Committee (Box-folder 10-3)
  - Call to St. Andrews (Box-folder 10-4)
  - Call to St. James--Houston (Box-folder 10-5)
  - Camp Tockwogh (Box-folder 10-6)
  - Children's Work Committee (Box-folder 10-7)
  - Clericus of Delaware (Box-folder 10-8)
  - Completion of Bethlehem, The (Box-folder 10-9)
  - Department of Christian Education (Box-folder 10-10)
  - Ehart, Edward (Box-folder 10-11)
  - Ethics and Economic Life (Box-folder 10-12)
  - Diocese of Delaware--General (Box-folder 10-13)
  - Diocesan Dates (Box-folder 10-14)
  - Every Member Canvass (Box-folder 10-15, 16, 17, 18)
  - Examining Chaplains (Box-folder 11-1)
  - Family and Religion (Box-folder 11-2)
  - Feelers (Box-folder 11-3)
  - Bryan Green Mission (Box-folder 11-4)
  - Hood Conference (Box-folder 11-5)
  - Interfaith Committee (Box-folder 11-6)
  - Lent--1954 (Box-folder 11--7)
  - Letters--Birmingham (Box-folder 11-8)
  - St. Andrews Alter Guild (Box-folder 11-9)
  - St. Andrews Church School (Box-folder 11-10)
  - WDEL Radio Broadcasts (Box-folder 11-11)
  - Youth of St. Andrews (Box-folder 11-12)
- Bishop of Southwestern Virginia 1954-1979
  190 linear inches (38 document boxes)This series encompasses Marmion's administrative record as Bishop of the Diocese of Southwestern Virginia, as well as several topics he took interest in. Divided into four sub-series: Administration, Civil Rights, International Affair, and the Vietnam War.
  - Administrative Files
    Contains general administrative files relating to the Diocese of Southwestern Virginia and Marmion's duties in the Episcopal Church. Information includes a broad range of topics, including committee reports, diocesan reports, projects and programs undertaken by both the church and diocese, and correspondence related to the day to day operations of the diocese
    - Academy of Parish Clergy (Box-folder 12-1)
    - Advance Fund--Memorials (Box-folder 12-2)
    - Aging (Box-folder 12-3)
    - Aging--Home for the Elderly (Box-folder 12-4)
    - Appalachia Division (Box-folder 12-5,6)
    - Architecture and Construction Committee (Box-folder 12-7)
    - Bishop's Advisory Council on Applicants for the Ministry (Box-folder 12-8, 9, 10)
    - Bishop's invitational Conference (Box-folder 12-11)
    - Bishop Marmion's Consecration (Box-folder 12-12)
    - Bishop's Nominating Committee (Box-folder 13-1)
    - Bishop's Orientation Conference (Box-folder 13-2)
    - Black Ministries Commission (Box-folder 13-3)
    - Boundary Commission (Box-folder 13-4, 5, 6, 7)
    - Boy's Home (Map-case 13-8)
    - Cabinet (Box-folder 14-1)
    - Campbell, Wilburn (Box-folder 14-2)
    - Cathedral (Diocese) (Box-folder 14-3)
    - Central House for Deaconesses (Box-folder 14-4)
    - Certified Workers (Box-folder 14-5)
    - Chancellor (Box-folder 14-6)
    - Charismatic Movement (Box-folder 14-7)
    - Child Care Centers (Box-folder 14-8)
    - Choirmaster (Box-folder 14-9)
    - Christian Education--Auto Visual (Box-folder 14-10)
    - Christian Education--Youth Reports (Box-folder 14-11)
    - Christian Education Conference (Box-folder 14-12)
    - Christian Social Relations (Box-folder 14-13,14)
    - Christian Housing Program (Box-folder 14-15)
    - Church Life Insurance Corporation (Box-folder 14-16)
    - Church Music (Box-folder 14-17)
    - Church Periodical Club (Box-folder 14-18)
    - Church Property Committee (Box-folder 14-19)
    - Church and Society (Box-folder 15-1)
    - Church Society for College Work (Box-folder 15-2)
    - Clergy Compensation and Performance Evaluation (Box-folder 15-3)
    - Clergy--Continuing Education (Box-folder 15-4)
    - Clergy Development Committee (Box-folder 15-5)
    - Clergy Prospects (Box-folder 15-6,7)
    - Clergy--Social Security (Box-folder 15-8)
    - College of Preachers (Box-folder 15-9)
    - College Work (Box-folder 15-10)
    - Commission on Ministry (Box-folder 15-11)
    - Commission on Ministry--Minutes (Box-folder 15-12)
    - Commission on Housing and Service for the Aging and Elderly (Box-folder 15-13)
    - Committee (Box-folder 15-14)
    - Community Action (Box-folder 15-15)
    - Community of the Way of the Cross, The (Box-folder 15-16)
    - Conference for the New Ministries (Box-folder 15-17)
    - Congressional Development Office (Box-folder 16-1)
    - Congressional Development--Applicants (Box-folder 16-2)
    - Consent (Box-folder 16-3)
    - Constitution and Canons (Box-folder 16-4,5)
    - Consultation on Church Unions (Box-folder 16-6,7)
    - Consultant to Vacancies--Parishes (Box-folder 16-8)
    - Continuing Education Diocese (Box-folder 16-9)
    - Convocations--General (Box-folder 17-1)
    - Corbin Fund (Box-folder 17-2)
    - Council of the Southern Mountains (Box-folder 17-3)
    - Council (Box-folder 17-4,5,6,7,8)
    - Counseling--Clergy Families (Box-folder 17-9)
    - Craighill Memorial (Box-folder 17-10)
    - Crisis in American Life Program (Box-folder 17-11)
    - Criteria for Selecting Priorities (Box-folder 17-12)
    - Crop (Box-folder 17-13)
    - Cuttington College (Box-folder 18-1)
    - Deaf Work (Box-folder 18-2)
    - Death With Dignity (Box-folder 18-3)
    - Dees, James Parker (Box-folder 18-4)
    - Deferred Gifts Division (Box-folder 18-5)
    - Delta Ministry--Greenville, Mississippi (Box-folder 18-6)
    - Department Heads (Box-folder 18-7)
    - Dialogue (Box-folder 18-8)
    - Dickenson County Food Cooperative (Box-folder 18-9)
    - Diocesan Information (Box-folder 18-10)
    - Diocesan Library (Box-folder 18-11)
    - Diocesan Personnel File (Box-folder 18-12)
    - Diocesan Programs Funded (Box-folder 18-13)
    - Diocesan Strategy Committee (Box-folder 18-14)
    - Dissent (Box-folder 18-15)
    - Ecumenical Commission (Box-folder 18-16)
    - Ecumenical Relations (Box-folder 18-17)
    - Episcopal Church Center (Box-folder 18-19)
    - Episcopal Church Foundation (Box-folder 18-20)
    - Episcopal Church Women (Box-folder 18-21)
    - Episcopal Church Women--Triennial (Box-folder 18-22)
    - Episcopal Church Women (Box-folder 18-23)
    - Episcopal Colleges (Box-folder 19-1)
    - Episcopal Day School (Box-folder 19-2,3)
    - Episcopal Radio--TV Foundation (Box-folder 19-4)
    - Episcopal School Foundation
    - Episcopal Society for Ministering to the Aging, INC (Box-folder 19-6)
    - Episcopal Society for Ministry in Higher Education (Box-folder 19-7)
    - Episcopalian, The (Box-folder 19-8)
    - Equal Opportunity Employment Task Force (Box-folder 19-9)
    - Evan's House (Box-folder 19-10)
    - Evangelical Education Society (Box-folder 19-11)
    - Evangelism and Renewal (Box-folder 19-12)
    - Every Member Canvass (Box-folder 19-13)
    - Executive Board (Box-folder 19-14)
    - Executive Board--Visitations (Box-folder 19-15)
    - Executive Board--Brochures (Box-folder 19-16)
    - Executive Council (Box-folder 20-1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8)
    - Faith Alive (Box-folder 20-9)
    - Finance (Box-folder 20-10)
    - Financial Appeals--Response (Box-folder 20-11)
    - Fish (Box-folder 20-12)
    - Fund for an Open Society (Box-folder 21-1)
    - Future of the Diocese, The (Box-folder 21-2)
    - General Convention (Box-folder 21-3)
    - General Convention--Additional Representatives (Box-folder 21-4)